[{"A": "the completion of the transcontinental railway", "B": "the execution of the Chicago Seven", "question": "\"Standby, we've done praying.\" This famous quotation is attributed to the occasion of:", "E": "the ratification of the Bill of Rights.", "D": "the completion of the Panama Canal", "answer": "A", "C": "the invention of the telephone", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Ford", "B": "Eli Whitney", "question": "\u201cEverything can be done faster and better.\u201d This saying is attributed to:", "E": "Benjamin Franklin.", "D": "Taylor", "answer": "A", "C": "Edison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The lunar calendar was good for agriculture.", "B": "Scientists are not concerned with material goods.", "question": "\u201cThe Lunar Society\u201d was an organization that believed:", "D": "Reaching the moon would stimulate the U.S. economy.", "answer": "C", "C": "The good life is based on having adequate material goods.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "water pumps.", "B": "elevators.", "question": "A key to deep coal mining success in England was the invention of:", "E": "individual oxygen supplies for each miner.", "D": "electric engines.", "answer": "A", "C": "a better pick.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "save the pigeons", "B": "planned obsolescence", "question": "A theme of Pigeon Impossible was:", "E": "the beauty of nature", "D": "waterfowl forever", "answer": "C", "C": "unintended consequences", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The damage to Earth is already beyond the control of humankind and decline in our quality of life is inevitable.", "B": "There is still hope for maintaining a good quality of life if we maintain our respect for the Earth.", "question": "A view expressed in Maxidiwiac is that:", "D": "none of the above.", "answer": "B", "C": "This is not true. The three films each present significantly different points of view.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the British.", "B": "the French.", "question": "According to Bronowski, the steam-powered railroad engine was the invention of", "D": "the Americans.", "answer": "A", "C": "the Polish.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Nikola Tesla", "B": "J.J. Thomson", "question": "According to Bronowski, this person was the inventor of the steam locomotive:", "E": "Richard Trevithick", "D": "Nikolai Slavyanov", "answer": "E", "C": "Marten Triewald", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Williamsburg", "B": "Washington", "question": "According to Cooke, this was the central city of colonial America:", "E": "Boston.", "D": "Jamestown", "answer": "C", "C": "Philadelphia", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "automatic devices", "B": "public works and industrial development", "question": "According to Jacob Bronowski, in the 18th century English inventors and engineers were leaders in:", "D": "the development of thrashing machines.", "answer": "B", "C": "export of technological know-how worldwide.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "automatic devices", "B": "public works and industrial development", "question": "According to Jacob Bronowski, in the 18th century French and Swiss inventors and engineers were leaders in", "D": "the development of thrashing machines.", "answer": "A", "C": "export of technological know-how worldwide.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "would place greater emphasis on science and mathematics.", "B": "puts greater emphasis on human concerns than usually happened in the past, but without sacrificing good scientific principles.", "question": "According to Rogers, a holistic approach to technology or engineering design:", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "would root engineering design on a comprehensive sociological study of human convictions.", "answer": "B", "C": "would emphasize a broader base of social concern and design based on a blessed human instinct.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "contributes heavily to environmental pollution.", "B": "was developed by another company.", "question": "According to Rogers, some businesses fund essential product development by selling a product that", "D": "A and C above.", "answer": "D", "C": "they know to be inadequate.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Francis", "B": "Jones", "question": "After the American Civil War, this person designed improved gun carriages, turrets, and war vessels.", "E": "Eads.", "D": "Whitney", "answer": "E", "C": "Latrobe", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "was nonexistent prior to the coming of Europeans.", "B": "involved only gathering of wild plants that existed in the river valleys.", "question": "Agriculture among Native Americans in what is now North Dakota:", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "A and B above.", "answer": "C", "C": "involved fields of corn that were of moderate size.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "American politicians who had been educated in England.", "B": "The \u201crude men of the back country.\u201d", "question": "Alistair Cooke claimed that the real heroes in the development of the U.S. were:", "D": "Inventor-statesmen such as Franklin and Jefferson.", "answer": "B", "C": "The minutemen of the Continental Army.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "A good horse", "B": "Buffalo cakes", "question": "Alistair Cooke claims that homesteaders needed three basic items of technology in order to survive. Onewas:", "E": "Barbed wire.", "D": "Sugar and salt for the long winters", "answer": "E", "C": "A good load of fire wood", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "1885-1895", "B": "1865-1875", "question": "American military forces were used against native Americans in South Dakota and striking workers inPullman, Illinois in this time period:", "E": "1910-1920.", "D": "1810-1819", "answer": "A", "C": "1820-1830", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "steel", "B": "stone", "question": "American public works in the 18th century made heavy use of:", "D": "an early plastic compound", "answer": "C", "C": "wood", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Francis", "B": "Jones", "question": "An accomplished engineer, this person was warm and gregarious by nature, published the results ofcollaborative research and trained a generation of younger engineers:", "E": "Eads.", "D": "Whitney", "answer": "A", "C": "Latrobe", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "To construct wooden buildings coated with natural fats.", "B": "To construct wooden buildings using very thick timbers.", "question": "An early fire protection technique used in the colonial period in America was:", "D": "To construct wooden buildings only if they could be located with 100 feet of a fire hydrant.", "answer": "B", "C": "To construct wooden buildings using thin sheets of wood so that one could easily break through the wall to escape a fire.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "one of the seven wonders of the ancient world", "B": "first invented by Edison shortly after the invention of the light bulb", "question": "An early lighthouse was:", "D": "erected at Plymouth rock to guide the Pilgrims safely to land.", "answer": "A", "C": "invented by the British at about the time of the American Revolution", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "railroad", "B": "telegraph", "question": "An English editor wrote what follows in an 1835 magazine. It \u201cwill give anunnatural impetus to society, destroy all the relations that exist between man and man, overthrow allmercantile regulations, and create, at the peril of life, all sorts of confusion and distress.\u201d This editorwas referring to the", "E": "river boat.", "D": "machine gun", "answer": "A", "C": "balloon", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Blanchard lathe", "B": "axe", "question": "An example of an American tool that was developed by trial and error and also helped start America\u2019swood industry was the:", "D": "hammer", "answer": "B", "C": "chainsaw", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "You have taken trouble with nothing in life except to get rich.", "B": "You have taken trouble with nothing in life except to oppress the poor.", "question": "Beaumarchais\u2019 charge against the noblemen of France was essentially:", "E": "You have taken trouble with nothing in life except to be born.", "D": "You have taken trouble with nothing in life except to deceive the King.", "answer": "E", "C": "You have taken trouble with nothing in life except to gain the King\u2019s favor.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "1740-1759", "B": "1760-1779", "question": "Ben Franklin\u2019s experiment with lightning to show that it was electricity was conducted in the period:", "E": "1820-1850.", "D": "1800-1819", "answer": "A", "C": "1780-1799", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "finding jobs for many skilled Europeans and Americans.", "B": "bringing the professional engineering skills of planning, organizing, and directing technical projects to America.", "question": "Benjamin Henry Latrobe aided in the transfer of technology to America by:", "D": "none of the above.", "answer": "C", "C": "A and B.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "\u201cfather of Scientific Management.\u201d", "B": "\u201cfather of agricultural engineering.\u201d", "question": "Best known for his invention of the cotton gin, Eli Whitney is commonly called:", "D": "\u201cfather of technology transfer.\u201d", "answer": "C", "C": "\u201cfather of American technology.\u201d", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Central heating provided by natural gas", "B": "High wages available from only part-time labor", "question": "Bronowski argued that the housewife of the last century benefited tremendously from:", "D": "Iron products for the home.", "answer": "D", "C": "Use of gas- or electric-powered refrigerators", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "gift of the Renaissance was the emergence of the dignity of humankind while the contribution of the Industrial Revolution was an understanding of the unity of nature.", "B": "gift of the Industrial Revolution was the emergence of the dignity of humankind while the contribution of the Renaissance was an understanding of the unity of nature.", "question": "Bronowski argues that the great:", "E": "mistake of the Renaissance was the emergence of the idea of the dignity of humankind while the the great mistake of the Industrial Revolution belief in the unity of nature.", "D": "gift of the Renaissance was the emergence of the dignity of humankind while the Industrial Revolution led to much confusion about ideas of the unity of nature.", "answer": "A", "C": "mistake of the Renaissance was the invention of the idea of the dignity of humankind while the contribution of the Industrial Revolution was an understanding of the unity of nature.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "To leave behind a record of their culture and values.", "B": "To fill leisure time especially during the long years in which they were confined to the caves due to the ice age.", "question": "Bronowski argues that the immediate ancestors of modern humans used cave paintings:", "E": "To teach their people respect for all animal life.", "D": "To satisfy creative urges that were much more important than survival instincts.", "answer": "C", "C": "As part of ritualistic training and preparation for hunting.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "invented bifocals to improve his understanding of spoken French.", "B": "invented the hearing-aid to improve his understanding of spoken French.", "question": "Bronowski claims that Benjamin Franklin:", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "didn\u2019t have any part of the writing of the Declaration of Independence.", "answer": "A", "C": "didn\u2019t, in fact, make any significant contributions to the understanding of electricity.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Railroads", "B": "Steamboats.", "question": "Certain technologies have been heavily dependent on a multitude of minor improvements. Examples are:", "E": "A and B only.", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "D", "C": "Petroleum refining.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "2,000 to 3,000 years ago", "B": "200 to 300 years ago", "question": "Crop agriculture was first developed about", "E": "almost 100,000 years ago.", "D": "8,000 to 10,000 years ago", "answer": "D", "C": "150 to 200 years ago", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "telegraph", "B": "reaper", "question": "Cyrus Hall McCormick invented the _____________.", "D": "interchangeable parts", "answer": "B", "C": "sewing machine", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "10,000 tons of coal per year.", "B": "10 million tons of coal per year.", "question": "Deep mining in England around 1800 yielded about:", "E": "one million tons of coal per year.", "D": "no coal. England imported all its coal from Germany.", "answer": "B", "C": "no coal. England imported all its coal from the U.S.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "10 chromosomes", "B": "14 chromosomes", "question": "Domesticated agriculture has its origin in wild grasses. One of these was goat grass. Goat grass has:", "E": "an odd number of chromosomes.", "D": "28 chromosomes", "answer": "B", "C": "16 chromosomes", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "12 chromosomes", "B": "14 chromosomes", "question": "Domesticated agriculture has its origin in wild grasses. One of these was wild wheat. Wild wheat has:", "E": "an odd number of chromosomes.", "D": "28 chromosomes", "answer": "B", "C": "20 chromosomes", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The costs of this education were too great, and the length of class periods was too short.", "B": "Government standards were not sufficient, and federal funding was not available.", "question": "Dr. Thomas P. Jones perceived two central flaws in the technical education system of the United States inthe mid-1800\u2019s. What were these two flaws?", "D": "Technological teachers were not trained well enough for the growing number of these students, and teaching centers such as colleges were not large enough.", "answer": "C", "C": "Elementary school teaching created differences between private and open schools, and apprenticeship systems failed to encourage technological progress.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "St. Louis", "B": "Minneapolis", "question": "Ead\u2019s Bridge was built in 1874. Which city is it in?", "D": "New York", "answer": "A", "C": "New Orleans", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "10-14 hours", "B": "100-140 hours", "question": "Edison was the first person to develop a light bulb that offered a reasonable lifetime. It was about:", "D": "10,000-14,000 hours", "answer": "C", "C": "1,000-1,400 hours", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "philosophy and the classics.", "B": "science and engineering.", "question": "Edwin Layton claims that the United States Military Academy was founded with a curriculum strong in:", "E": "American know-how.", "D": "French law", "answer": "A", "C": "Prussian militarism", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "his love for firearms.", "B": "his military expertise.", "question": "Eli Whitney agreed to a contract for producing 10,000 regulation muskets for Oliver Wolcott due to:", "answer": "B", "C": "his financial struggle.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "an engineer responsible for improving the production of steel in the U.S.", "B": "an ancestor of bread wheat.", "question": "Emmer was", "D": "an evolutionary failure since it had an uneven number of chromosomes.", "answer": "B", "C": "a wild grass discovered by native Americans that revolutionized American farming.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "steel", "B": "stone", "question": "English public works in the 18th century made heavy use of:", "D": "an early plastic compound", "answer": "B", "C": "wood", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jefferson", "B": "McCormick", "question": "Following in his father\u2019s footsteps, this inventor developed a machine of tremendous importance infarming. His success in business and technological development led him to dominate his field, becomevery wealthy, and help fund seminaries.", "E": "Eads.", "D": "Whitney", "answer": "B", "C": "Deere", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The mathematical theory was too complex. Even though the results were right, no one understood them.", "B": "The mathematical theory was too idealized or simplified.", "question": "Francis faced problems in applying the turbine theory of the day. One of these was that:", "D": "Experimental studies, though done properly, were not adequately understood.", "answer": "B", "C": "Friction was given too prominent a place in the analysis.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Bell", "B": "Francis", "question": "He battled tuberculosis during his adult life:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "C", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Bell", "B": "Francis", "question": "He called one of his first inventions a \u201csubmarine\u201d:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "C", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "He pioneered business techniques such as credit selling and mass advertising:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "A", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "He planned a ship-railway across the Mexican isthmus of Tehuantepec:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "C", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Boulton", "B": "Wilkinson", "question": "He said that energy is eternal delight:", "E": "Blake.", "D": "Wedgwood", "answer": "E", "C": "Franklin", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Volti", "B": "Pursell", "question": "He said that many inventions are as pointless as going to the moon:", "E": "Bronowski.", "D": "Kostof", "answer": "E", "C": "Cooke", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "He was a designer of ironclad boats:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "C", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Rockefeller", "B": "Carnegie", "question": "He was the driller of the first productive oil well in the United states:", "E": "Cricket", "D": "Drake", "answer": "D", "C": "Bell", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jones", "B": "Boyden", "question": "He wrote about the history of river navigation in America:", "E": "Eads", "D": "McCormick", "answer": "C", "C": "Gould", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "contributed much to the development of the steel industry.", "B": "were pioneering shipbuilders.", "question": "Henry Bessemer and Andrew Carnegie", "D": "supported Land\u2019s camera research.", "answer": "A", "C": "helped found the University of Virginia.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Latrobe", "B": "Jones", "question": "His ideas were probably shaped by his early association with Joseph Priestley and his practical interestswere shown by his involvement in a fire engine manufacturing firm:", "E": "Boyden.", "D": "Eads", "answer": "B", "C": "Francis", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "His invention was entered in competitions at international exhibitions in Europe in the second half of the19th century:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "A", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Isaac Newton", "B": "Galileo", "question": "His son built the first clock that used a pendulum escapement:", "D": "Benjamin Franklin", "answer": "B", "C": "Thomas Edison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The federal government\u2019s insistence that contractors share information with the national armories.", "B": "Private armorers excelled at ferreting out technical innovations created elsewhere.", "question": "How did arms manufacturers have access to the latest technologies in the 1820\u2019s and the 1830\u2019s?", "E": "All of the above.", "D": "A and B.", "answer": "D", "C": "Through regional organizations of technicians.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "None.", "B": "One.", "question": "In 1800 about this many steam engines were available in the United States:", "E": "200 to 400.", "D": "2 dozen to 4 dozen.", "answer": "C", "C": "2 to 4.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "In 1847 he built a farm equipment factory in Chicago:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "A", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "steel plow", "B": "steam engine", "question": "In Domesticating a Wilderness, it was said that John Deere invented what?", "D": "thrashing machine", "answer": "D", "C": "Virginia reaper", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Vigorously opposed technological progress due to its damage to the environment.", "B": "Vigorously opposed modern science due to its damage to religion.", "question": "In lecture the instructor has:", "E": "A, B, and C.", "D": "None of the above.", "answer": "D", "C": "Vigorously opposed technological progress due to its damage to human individuality.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "a mobile military group.", "B": "a rural transit system.", "question": "In Philadelphia in 1798, Benjamin Latrobe presented the idea for:", "D": "a steam-powered waterworks.", "answer": "D", "C": "an illuminated sundial.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Moscow", "B": "The Pentagon", "question": "In Pigeon Impossible, the intercontinental ballistic missile\u2019s assigned target was:", "E": "The Three Gorges Dam", "D": "Bagdad, Iraq", "answer": "A", "C": "Tehran, Iran", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "steam engine", "B": "electricity", "question": "In the 1700\u2019s, what was the basic source of power for industry?", "D": "primitive petroleum products.", "answer": "C", "C": "water wheel", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Under $5", "B": "Between $10 and $50.", "question": "In the mid-19th century mass-produced plows sold for:", "D": "None of the above. They weren\u2019t mass-produced.", "answer": "A", "C": "Between $100 and $200.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "were governed by the clock and always on a set schedule.", "B": "valued their labor and time immensely.", "question": "In the Middle Ages in a pre-industrialized community, people:", "D": "charged a lot for time spent on products and work done.", "answer": "C", "C": "opened and closed their shops when they wanted and were not ruled by the clock.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Bell Telephone System", "B": "Western Union", "question": "In the nineteenth century, this was one of the largest corporations in America:", "E": "Columbia Broadcasting System", "D": "General Motors", "answer": "B", "C": "Wells Fargo", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "wooden plows", "B": "turbines", "question": "James Francis worked with and designed:", "D": "sailing ships.", "answer": "B", "C": "cotton gins", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "in Philadelphia with Franklin\u2019s support.", "B": "in Boulton\u2019s factory.", "question": "James Watt built his steam engine", "D": "in Lowell, Mass.", "answer": "B", "C": "in London in Holmes\u2019 Baker Street Factory.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "5,000-7,000", "B": "12,000-15,000", "question": "Jefferson sold his own books to the Library of Congress. How many books were involved?", "D": "25,000-26,000", "answer": "A", "C": "1,000-2,000", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "science", "B": "industry", "question": "Jefferson thought that this was more important in a republic than in any other government.", "D": "capitalism", "answer": "A", "C": "education", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the Declaration of Independence", "B": "the ratification of the U.S. Constitution", "question": "Jefferson's library formed the nucleus of the new Library of Congress on the occasion of:", "E": "the burning of the national Capitol in Philadelphia.", "D": "the founding of the American Philosophical Society", "answer": "C", "C": "the burning of the national Capitol in 1814", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "steel plow", "B": "steam engine", "question": "John Deere invented the:", "D": "thrashing machine", "answer": "A", "C": "Virginia reaper", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Raising reindeer.", "B": "By being very successful dairy farmers.", "question": "Laplanders have survived through the centuries:", "D": "By following reindeer herds and harvesting the entire animal very efficiently.", "answer": "D", "C": "Hunting reindeer much like Americans hunt deer.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "help engineers design more successful and appropriate products.", "B": "help educators design curricula that are relevant to societal needs.", "question": "Lifelong study of the Impact of Technology on Society will:", "E": "A, B, and C.", "D": "only A and B.", "answer": "E", "C": "help consumers make appropriate decisions in use of technology.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "5-10 feet", "B": "11-20 feet", "question": "Mandan earth lodges had a diameter of about:", "E": "51-100 feet", "D": "31-50 feet", "answer": "D", "C": "21-30 feet", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Big River Woman", "B": "Stone-Bird Woman", "question": "Maxidiwiac is a name that means:.", "D": "Buffalo Skin Woman", "answer": "C", "C": "Buffalo-Bird Woman", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "aid monks in scheduling religious prayers, masses, and other religious observations.", "B": "help farmers in planting.", "question": "Motivation(s) for the development of the clock was (or were) to:", "E": "A and D.", "D": "regulate the irrigation of land.", "answer": "E", "C": "regulate the length of government meetings.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Old English for Navies.", "B": "Old English for Navigation.", "question": "Navvies refers to", "D": "Small boats used for transportation along the waterways in England.", "answer": "C", "C": "The worker who dug trenches or canals in England.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "radio.", "B": "pony express.", "question": "News of the completion of the transcontinental railroad was communicated by:", "D": "telephone.", "answer": "C", "C": "telegraph.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "religion was a minor part of everyday life", "B": "the absolute subservience of women was divinely ordained", "question": "Nineteen-century North Dakota Native Americans shared this concept with ancient Hebrew culture:", "answer": "C", "C": "the woman of the house held a key or central role in all of family life.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "from reservation seed stores", "B": "from the U.S. army of occupation", "question": "North Dakota Native Americans obtained their seeds for the coming year\u2019s crops:", "D": "from saving seeds from their best plants.", "answer": "D", "C": "from saving seeds from the plants they couldn\u2019t manage to eat.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "government efforts to effectively control the populations of wild birds", "B": "the great risks involved in the creation and use of high tech devices", "question": "On the serious side, the theme of Pigeon Impossible was:", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "both B and C above.", "answer": "B", "C": "the fallacies in the evidence for global climate change as presented in An Inconvenient Truth.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jefferson.", "B": "Mason", "question": "Over and over again, this person wrote of the essential \u201cgoodness and wisdom\u201d of the common people.", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Hamilton", "answer": "A", "C": "Madison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "in the 16th century due to drainage to make the elaborate canal system.", "B": "over the past two centuries due to acid rain.", "question": "Peat bogs in England died:", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "in the past half century due to nuclear fallout.", "answer": "B", "C": "in the 1970\u2019s due to widespread use of DDT.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "are found in the Book of Jericho in the Christian Scriptures.", "B": "cannot be found anywhere in Pre-Christian writings.", "question": "Possible references to early agricultural experiences of human beings", "D": "are found in Genesis in the Hebrew Scriptures.", "answer": "D", "C": "were purged from the Hebrew Scriptures by 12th century BCE city dwellers.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Things are getting better and better.", "B": "A penny saved is a penny earned.", "question": "Priestley, the Puritan chemist and minister, probably invented the phrase:", "D": "The greatest happiness for the greatest number.", "answer": "D", "C": "The end justifies the means.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "disliked the government's role in disseminating information useful to the citizens", "B": "conceived government's role to be that of disseminating information useful to the citizens rather than insuring material profit for innovators.", "question": "Regarding technological advances, Jefferson", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "conceived government's role to be insuring material profit for innovators rather than that of disseminating information useful to the citizens.", "answer": "B", "C": "denied government's role to be either insuring material profit for innovators or disseminating information useful to the citizens.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Ann Carlson", "B": "Maxidiwiac", "question": "She believed that we would survive if we maintained our respect for the earth:", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Jane Goodall", "answer": "B", "C": "Marie Curie", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "were gifts to American settlers from Native Americans.", "B": "were invented in America in the late 17th century.", "question": "Significant devices and techniques that had a powerful impact on American agriculture were the horsecollar, the heavy plow, and the three-field system of crop rotation. These devices and techniques:", "E": "were brought to American by the first European settlers.", "D": "were brought to American by Irish immigrants in the late 19th century.", "answer": "E", "C": "were invented in America in the late 18th century.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "in the history of the world was most prominent in the United States.", "B": "was significant in ancient Rome. About one-third of the population was in slavery.", "question": "Slavery:", "answer": "B", "C": "is an institution that had its beginnings in the Christian church.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "16 chromosomes", "B": "20 chromosomes", "question": "Some historians of science believe that by some genetic accident, goat grass and wild wheat combined toform Emmer. Emmer crossed with another natural goat grass and produced a still larger hybrid with 42chromosomes, which is bread wheat. Emmer had:", "E": "an odd number of chromosomes.", "D": "38 chromosomes", "answer": "C", "C": "28 chromosomes", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Internal combustion engine", "B": "Computers", "question": "The \u201cAnalytical Engine\u201d was a step in the development of which of the following?", "D": "Large scale construction", "answer": "B", "C": "Assembly lines", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "River transport of supplies", "B": "Crop agriculture", "question": "The 19th century Indians of North Dakota had technologies to deal with:", "E": "Only B and C above", "D": "All of the above", "answer": "D", "C": "Clothes and footwear", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "1840\u2019s.", "B": "1790\u2019s.", "question": "The age of tech farming began in Europe and North America in:", "D": "1920\u2019s.", "answer": "A", "C": "1890\u2019s.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Believed that England would be better off without the American colonies.", "B": "Believed that all men were created equal.", "question": "The British government suspected that the ironmasters of the eighteen century:", "D": "Were withholding knowledge of significant inventions that ultimately led to the loss of the American colonies.", "answer": "B", "C": "Should control the gold that belonged to the British crown.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Germany", "B": "Poland", "question": "The Central Pacific portion of the first transcontinental railway was built largely by immigrants from:", "E": "Mexico and other Latin American countries.", "D": "China", "answer": "D", "C": "Italy and France", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "L\u2019Enfant", "B": "Madison", "question": "The designer of Washington, D.C. was:", "D": "Ben Franklin", "answer": "A", "C": "Spiro Kostof", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "slave labor.", "B": "petrochemicals.", "question": "The development of the industrial revolution was heavily dependent on:", "D": "the clock.", "answer": "D", "C": "the French Revolution.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "France", "B": "Russia", "question": "The early work of Francis relied on data on the strength of iron developed by engineers and scientists inthis country:", "E": "U.S.A.", "D": "Britain", "answer": "D", "C": "The Netherlands", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "10 to 20 men.", "B": "70 to 80 horses.", "question": "The first combines were pulled by:", "D": "30 to 40 horses.", "answer": "D", "C": "5 to 15 horses.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "1765-1774", "B": "1775-1784", "question": "The first United States patent law was passed in the period:", "E": "1805-1814.", "D": "1795-1804", "answer": "C", "C": "1785-1794", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Dallas-Fort Worth", "B": "Houston-Grand Island, Nebraska", "question": "The focus of 19th century cattle trade was", "D": "Albuquerque-El Paso", "answer": "C", "C": "Abilene, Kansas and Chicago", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Franklin.", "B": "Whitney.", "question": "The following person can be thought of as the father of the military-industrial complex:", "D": "Latrobe.", "answer": "B", "C": "McCormick.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "nomadic tribes that possessed their own herds.", "B": "hunter-gatherers who followed natural animal migrations.", "question": "The immediate ancestors of prehistoric village dwellers probably were", "D": "Mongol tribes of Central Asia.", "answer": "B", "C": "Ape-man tribes of Central Africa.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "were caught up with the idea of nature as a carrier of energy or font of power.", "B": "saw their works receive wide distribution due their ability to transmit their works by wire (teletype).", "question": "The Industrial Revolution had a significant impact on the Romantic poets of the late eighteenth century andearly nineteen century. The poets:", "D": "fought modern technology because it reduced the freedom of women.", "answer": "A", "C": "joined with the Luddittes in opposing the evils of modern technology.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "was fought by the French and the Swiss.", "B": "began in the heavily populated cities.", "question": "The Industrial Revolution:", "D": "did not include textile manufacturing.", "answer": "C", "C": "was begun in villages by craftspersons.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the railroad industry", "B": "the anti-slavery areas of the North", "question": "The Luddite movement began in:", "E": "the American shipbuilding industry at the time of the War of 1812.", "D": "the hosiery trades", "answer": "D", "C": "the U.S. automobile industry", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "threatening the quality of their lives.", "B": "inherently good.", "question": "The majority of people living in the 1950\u2019s felt that all of the technological advancements were", "D": "none of the above.", "answer": "B", "C": "causing energy shortages.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "a statue in Washington D.C.", "B": "Jefferson\u2019s home built and designed by himself.", "question": "The Monticello was", "D": "the town in which Jefferson lived.", "answer": "B", "C": "an early ironclad gunboat.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "iron tools", "B": "copper tools", "question": "The principal result of the Neolithic Revolution was the invention of:", "D": "crop agriculture.", "answer": "D", "C": "cave art", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "it was a primary building and manufacturing material.", "B": "it was a primary fuel of this era.", "question": "The ready availability of wood gave the Americans advantages that have seldom been appreciated. Woodwas a basic foundation of the economy because:", "E": "A and B only.", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "D", "C": "it was an important chemical product.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "an early copy machine", "B": "an early camera", "question": "The so-called \"polygraph\" was much admired by an American statesman. It was:", "E": "none of the above.", "D": "am early calculating machine", "answer": "A", "C": "an early lie detector", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "lives of bitter loneliness.", "B": "independent lives full of social and cultural involvements.", "question": "The spinsters of the early 1800\u2019s led:", "E": "were social ostracized and unemployable.", "D": "the development of the pro-slavery movement in New England in an effort to free themselves of the drudgery of textile industry work.", "answer": "B", "C": "nothing. This has nothing to do with this course.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "engineers in the military.", "B": "spinster labor.", "question": "The Supreme Court at one time approved and later disapproved:", "E": "the view that technical progress is always beneficial.", "D": "freedom of religion.", "answer": "C", "C": "child industrial labor.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "lead", "B": "iron", "question": "The type of clock that was the first to be mass produced and the cheapest was made out of:", "D": "copper", "answer": "C", "C": "wood", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "sometime in the period 1880-1900", "B": "sometime in the period 1901-1920", "question": "The U.S. Rural Electrification Administration was established:", "E": "sometime in the period 1951-1960", "D": "sometime in the period 1941-1950", "answer": "C", "C": "sometime in the period 1921-1940", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "in California.", "B": "in Nevada.", "question": "The U.S. transcontinental railroad was completed:", "D": "in Utah.", "answer": "D", "C": "on the California-Nevada border.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Lincoln", "B": "Grant", "question": "The United States Military Academy was founded by which President:", "E": "Washington", "D": "Madison", "answer": "C", "C": "Jefferson", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "destruction due to forest fires was a constant risk.", "B": "destruction by floods or enemies was common.", "question": "The winter lodges of North Dakota Native Americans tended to be temporary since:", "E": "Both B and D above.", "D": "stampeding buffalo commonly destroyed them.", "answer": "B", "C": "not applicable. North Dakota Native Americans spent their winters in the South.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Maxidiwiac", "B": "Blue Planet", "question": "The work of George Catlin and Frederick Wilson are significant components of the film:", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Sweet Fresh Water", "answer": "A", "C": "Picture Power", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Catlin and Bodmer", "B": "Wilson and McKinley", "question": "These artists documented the cultures of pre-European American civilization:", "E": "Both B and D.", "D": "Bodmer and Carson", "answer": "A", "C": "Bodmer and Davis", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Washington and John Adams", "B": "Jefferson and Washington", "question": "These people were two of the signers of the first U.S. patent:", "E": "Jefferson and Franklin", "D": "Jefferson and Andrew Jackson", "answer": "B", "C": "John Adams and John Quincy Adams", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Benjamin Franklin", "B": "Thomas Jefferson", "question": "This American scientist was often photographed with American presidents:", "D": "Eli Whitney", "answer": "C", "C": "Thomas Edison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Holmes", "B": "Watson", "question": "This British inventor profoundly influenced the Industrial Revolution through his work in turning the up-and-down motions of a piston into rotation:", "E": "Hooke", "D": "Kay", "answer": "C", "C": "Watt", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "tuberculosis", "B": "polio", "question": "This disease caused the death of more than half of the Hidatsa tribe over a century ago:", "E": "whooping cough", "D": "meningitis", "answer": "C", "C": "small pox", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jefferson", "B": "Latrobe", "question": "This early American leader in technology wrote that \u201cthere is scarcely any other subject so familiarlyspoken of , and so little understood, as the principles of mechanics, and one, therefore, in which quackery ismore certain of success.\u201d", "E": "Jones", "D": "Eads.", "answer": "E", "C": "Whitney", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jefferson.", "B": "Mason", "question": "This early American politician felt that: \u201cthis American world is not for me.\u201d", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Hamilton", "answer": "D", "C": "Madison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Burr", "B": "Henry", "question": "This early designer of an Iron bridge nearly lost his life due to his activities in France:", "E": "Adams.", "D": "Franklin", "answer": "C", "C": "Paine", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick\u2019s reaper.", "B": "Hussey\u2019s reaper.", "question": "This machine cut a swath 18 feet wide, thrashing, cleaning, and sacking grain as it moved along:", "E": "The combine.", "D": "Whitney\u2019s cotton gin.", "answer": "E", "C": "John Hall\u2019s thrasher.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Hamilton", "B": "Franklin", "question": "This man hoped to use his retirement years for the sustained study of natural science:", "E": "John Adams", "D": "Jefferson", "answer": "D", "C": "Washington", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Hamilton", "B": "Franklin", "question": "This man was the best scientist of the group listed:", "E": "John Adams", "D": "Jefferson", "answer": "B", "C": "Washington", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Ford", "B": "Edison", "question": "This man's advice to deal with the 19th century problem of crowding in American cities was to leave thecity:", "E": "Washington.", "D": "Jefferson", "answer": "A", "C": "Franklin", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Thomas Jefferson", "B": "Benjamin Henry Latrobe", "question": "This person undertook the redesign and construction of the United States Capitol and the White House, aswell as the Baltimore Cathedral:", "D": "Eli Whitney", "answer": "B", "C": "Benjamin Franklin", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jefferson.", "B": "Mason", "question": "This person was known as the \u201cfather of the dollar\u201d because of his advocacy of a decimal currency system.", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Hamilton", "answer": "A", "C": "Madison", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Mumford", "B": "Whitehead", "question": "This scientist observed some years ago that \u201cto quarrel with technology is to quarrel with the nature of man--just as if we were to quarrel with his upright gait, his symbolic imagination, (and) his faculty for speech.\u201d", "E": "Bronowski.", "D": "Bigelow", "answer": "E", "C": "Burke", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Harvard", "B": "Yale", "question": "This university maintains the largest collection of Edison\u2019s papers:", "E": "Dartmouth", "D": "Rochester", "answer": "C", "C": "Rutgers", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the completion of the transcontinental railway", "B": "the execution of the Chicago Seven", "question": "This was the occasion of a newspaper report from a famous city in which it announced \"the annexationof the United States.", "E": "the ratification of the Bill of Rights.", "D": "the completion of the Panama Canal", "answer": "A", "C": "the invention of the telephone", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "reflected his distaste for urban life.", "B": "was designed by French architect L\u2019Enfant.", "question": "Thomas Jefferson\u2019s University of Virginia", "E": "Both B and C above.", "D": "all of the above.", "answer": "A", "C": "was the first American university to offer electrical engineering.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "for the elite.", "B": "for the common man.", "question": "Thomas Jones thought that journals of technology should be:", "D": "for private universities.", "answer": "B", "C": "as technical as possible.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "U.S. Patent Office", "B": "U.S. Post Office", "question": "Thomas P. Jones was appointed head of what U.S. organization in 1828?", "D": "U.S. War Department", "answer": "A", "C": "U.S. Department of Agriculture", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the historical center of the USA.", "B": "the cultural center of the USA.", "question": "To Jefferson the site of Washington, DC was best thought of as:", "E": "the best site for his University of Virginia.", "D": "that Indian swamp in the wilderness.", "answer": "D", "C": "the political center of the USA.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Promoted technical innovation.", "B": "Impeded technical innovation.", "question": "Volti argues that the strong guilds in Europe:", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Both A and C.", "answer": "B", "C": "Contributed to developing new professions.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Both loved urban life.", "B": "Both hated urban life.", "question": "Walt Whitman and Henry David Thoreau", "D": "Loved rural life and urban life, respectively.", "answer": "C", "C": "Loved urban life and rural life, respectively.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "two-thirds", "B": "one-half", "question": "Water wheels as a source of power for industry early in the 18th century had a fundamental efficiency limitof approximately:", "E": "less than 10%.", "D": "three-fourths", "answer": "A", "C": "one-third", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Stewart Udall", "B": "Robert White-Stevens", "question": "We will survive if we maintain our respect for the earth. This is the view of:", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "Roger Christie", "answer": "C", "C": "Maxidiwiac", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "malaria", "B": "measles", "question": "What caused the death of about half of the tribe Maxidiwiac belonged to?", "D": "tuberculosis", "answer": "C", "C": "smallpox", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "the plow.", "B": "steam engine.", "question": "What invention turned the cowboy into a rancher?", "D": "barbed wire.", "answer": "D", "C": "the horse and buggy.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Jeffersonians", "B": "Luddites", "question": "What is the name given to people who see technology as a danger to society?", "D": "Scientists", "answer": "B", "C": "Communists", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Piers founded on bedrock at greater depths than ever before.", "B": "First large bridge that used steel as its principal structural members.", "question": "D.What made Ead\u2019s Bridge such a great engineering feat?", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "B", "C": "Arches were longer than any other built before.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "8\u201d x 8\u201d timbers", "B": "2\u201d x 12\u201d timbers", "question": "What type of lumber is used to build a balloon frame house?", "D": "2\u201d x 6\u201d boards", "answer": "C", "C": "2\u201d x 4\u201d boards", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "because Jefferson hated democrats.", "B": "because Jefferson supported the Navy and promoted the construction of 176 gunboats capable of defending harbors.", "question": "What was the main reason that the phrase \u201cJefferson\u2019s democratic sinking fund\u201d came about?", "D": "at the time Jefferson was President the government didn\u2019t have enough money from taxes to pay off the debts created during his term.", "answer": "B", "C": "because Jefferson had many reasons for wanting to support communism and throw out democracy.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Build up the dams immediately in time for the next flood.", "B": "Tell the business owners that it was impossible to stop the flooding.", "question": "When James B. Francis was put in charge of rebuilding a system of dams and canals at Lowell, Ma., whatwas his method of dealing with the situation?", "D": "Patiently gather data and then seek scientific solutions to the problem.", "answer": "D", "C": "Seek solutions and then gather data to check if it would work.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "United States", "B": "France", "question": "Where did the Industrial Revolution begin?", "D": "Germany", "answer": "C", "C": "Great Britain", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Madrid, Spain", "B": "Altamira, Spain", "question": "Where is the cave containing a 14,000 year-old painting of bison that was first discovered in 1879?", "D": "none of the above", "answer": "B", "C": "Lascavx, Spain", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Springfield", "B": "Harpers Ferry", "question": "Which armory made the first regular-issue rifle to be mass-produced with interchangeable parts?", "D": "Mill Rock", "answer": "B", "C": "Middletown", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "French Revolution", "B": "English Industrial Revolution", "question": "Which came first?", "E": "War of 1812.", "D": "Russian Revolution", "answer": "B", "C": "American Revolution", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Thomas Jefferson", "B": "George Washington", "question": "Which important man in American history was given the nickname \u201cChild of Nature from the Backwoods?\u201d", "E": "Tom Paine", "D": "Ben Franklin", "answer": "D", "C": "James Watt", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Create tools and technologies.", "B": "Dependent on tools and technologies.", "question": "Which is not characteristic of human beings?", "D": "Independent of tools and technologies.", "answer": "D", "C": "Gain and transmit knowledge.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "The role and status of women.", "B": "Bicycle, automobile and other industries.", "question": "Which of the following did the invention of the sewing machine influence?", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "D", "C": "The garment trade.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "He was born and educated in England.", "B": "He was known for his talent of lecturing on various aspects of science and its applications.", "question": "Which of the following is NOT true about Thomas P. Jones?", "D": "He became the editor of the Franklin Institute\u2019s Magazine which later led him to be appointed head of the U.S. Patent Office.", "answer": "C", "C": "He developed many new inventions in electrical communications including the loudspeaker.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "He was born and educated in England.", "B": "He was known for his talent of lecturing on various aspects of science and its applications.", "question": "Which of the following is NOT true about Thomas P. Jones?", "D": "He was the editor of the Franklin Institute\u2019s Magazine.", "answer": "C", "C": "He developed many new inventions in electrical communications including the loudspeaker.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Piers founded on shallow floats.", "B": "First large bridge that used steel in its principal structural members.", "question": "Which of the following made the Eads Bridge such a great engineering feat?", "E": "None of the above.", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "B", "C": "Arches were shorter than any other built before.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "A high labor turnover.", "B": "Whitney was popular with employees.", "question": "Which of the following was a characteristic of Whitney\u2019s Mill Rock Armory?", "D": "All of the above.", "answer": "A", "C": "Very uniform parts produced.", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "A bridge", "B": "Gunboat", "question": "While James Buchanan Eads was serving as a clerk on a boat in the Mississippi River, what did he design?", "D": "Diving-bell", "answer": "D", "C": "A New Steam Engine", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Thomas Jefferson", "B": "James Madison", "question": "Who believed that inventions were a cumulative process rather than a single fruit of genius, and thereforedisapproved of a monopoly patent grant on inventions because he believed that it was restricting to thefreedom of ideas?", "D": "George Washington", "answer": "A", "C": "Ben Franklin", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Ben Franklin", "B": "Jefferson", "question": "Who discovered that the pendulum could be used in a clock?", "D": "Newton", "answer": "C", "C": "Galileo", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "James Watt", "B": "George Washington", "question": "Who received Eli Whitney\u2019s cotton gin patent application in 1793?", "D": "John Davis", "answer": "C", "C": "Thomas Jefferson", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "Thomas Jefferson", "B": "Robert Fulton", "question": "Who was the inventor of underwater mines?", "D": "George Fleming", "answer": "B", "C": "Eli Whitney", "status": "ok"}, {"A": "McCormick", "B": "Francis", "question": "With Boyden, he did all experimentation on full-sized turbines, circumventing the unpredictable results ofmodel experiments:", "E": "Jones", "D": "Latrobe", "answer": "B", "C": "Eads", "status": "ok"}]
